Guide to the David Bushnell Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
David Bushnell papers
1783-1956
MS 1107
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
Miscellaneous papers by and about Bushnell. Only two items are in his hand: a letter (1787) claiming land due him as a result of his service in the American Revolution, and a description of a model for a sailing torpedo [1824?]. Papers on his inventions include a letter by Ezra Lee (1815) with an account of Bushnell's submarine and Lee's operation of it in August 1787 in New York harbor. Also three letters by Joel Abbot (1825) to Bushnell (then known as David Bush) on his attempts to promote Bushnell's naval warning device. Correspondence (1826-1827) between his executor and his heirs, Ezra and Nehemiah Bushnell of Saybrook, Connecticut, includes a final accounting of Bushnell's estate. In the later papers (1881-1956) are four letters to Anson Phelps Stokes with biographical information on Bushnell and publications on his submarine.
Bushnell, David, 1740-
Scope and Contents
The David Bushnell Papers consist of miscellaneous papers by and about the inventor David Bushnell. Only two items are in his hand: a letter (1787) claiming land due to him as a result of his service in the American Revolution, and a description of a model for a sailing torpedo [1824?]. Papers on his inventions include a letter by Ezra Lee (1815) with an account of Bushnell's submarine and Lee's operation of it in August 1787 in New York harbor. Also included are three letters by Joel Abbot (1825) to Bushnell (then known as David Bush) on his attempts to promote Bushnell's naval warning device. Correspondence (1826-1827) between his executor and his heirs, Ezra and Nehemiah Bushnell of Saybrook, Connecticut, includes a final accounting of Bushnell's estate. In the later papers (1881-1956) are four letters to Anson Phelps Stokes with biographical infrmation on Bushnell and publications on his submarine.
Biographical / Historical
David Bushnell: inventor of the submarine mine and the submarine; in 1779 captain of sapping and mining company in the Revolutionary Army; in 1783 placed in command of the Corps of Engineers; in 1795 taught in private schools and several years later began practicing medicine in Warrenton, Georgia.
Science; Submarine warfare; Submarines (Ships); Torpedoes; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Inventors; Abbot, Henry L.; Bushnell, David, 1740-; Lee, Ezra, 1749-1821; Schieffelin, Edward, 1847-1897
- Inventory
  - Personal Papers
    - Abbot, Joel. 3 ALS to David Bush with enclosure to Secretary of the Navy. Re: Bushnell's "device for drawing off the invading foes of our country...", 1825 January 19, February 28, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bushnell, David
      - 2 signed receipts (photostatic copies) for rations, 1783 July 4, 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - ALS to Captain Thomas Machin. [Re: Land due him as a result of his military service during the American Revolution], 1787 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Description of a model of a sailing torpedo, [ca. 1824?] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Estate
    - Bushnell, Nehemiah. Correspondence re: estate, 1827 May 16, 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Griswold, Charles. ALS to Ezra or Nehemiah Bushnell, 1826 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hargraves, George
      - 3 ALS to Ezra Bushnell re: Estate of "David Bush", 1826 January 26, March 17, August 16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 2 ALS to Ezra Bushnell re: Estate of "David Bush" with enclosure showing the accounts for the estate of David Bush, 1827 February 25, April 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Legal Documents:
      - Will (copy), 1820 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Indemnifying bond, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Receipt, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Writings about David Bushnell
    - Abbot, Henry L. "The beginning of Modern Submarine Warfare." N.Y., Battalion Press of the U.S. Corp of Engineers. 196p. [2 copies], 1881 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Lee, Ezra
      - ALS to David Humphreys. [Describing his operation of the Bushnell submarine in August of 1776. With a printed biographical note on Humphreys], 1815 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Biographical note, including information on the Lee letter in folder 11, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Newman, Louis I. "Sergeant Ezra Lee and his 'American Turtle'" (Poem), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous letters to Anson Phelps Stokes re: David Bushnell, 1911-1914 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous printed matter re: David Bushnell, 1867, 1875 January 2, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Schieffelin, Edward Loomis. "David Bushnell and the First American Submarine" [student paper], 1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)